Hey, hey, what's up, my friend? So, do
you know there there is a legendary
trader called Dan Zanger who
achieved a 29,233%
return over a 1-year period trading
chart patterns.
And you also have this guy called Andrea
Unger who won the World Cup of Trading
four times using algorithms.
And finally,
a market wizard called Ed Seykota who
took $5,000 and turned it into 16
million as a trend follower.
These are three different traders with
different strategies, personalities, and
approaches towards the market.
But they all understood one thing that
95% of traders never figure out.
It's this. It's not a secret indicator.
It's not some magic candlestick pattern,
and it's not discipline.
It is this, the math behind profitable
trading.
And once you understand this math,
you'll see why a trading system with a
40% winning rate can absolutely crush
a system with an 80% winning rate.
Right? No, I haven't lost my mind. I
just lost my hair. The mind is still
intact. So, you ready? Then let's get
started. Let me ask you, if I give you a
trading system that has a 80% winning
rate, meaning you win 80% of the time,
will you trade it?
Well, many traders would say, "Hell yes,
Rayner. Give me that system. Take my
money. Take my wife." Well, okay. Maybe
not my wife, but you get the idea. So,
but what if I tell you that this same
system could still
cause you to lose money in the long run.
How is that possible?
Because your winning rate is only half
the story.
And this is where most traders get it
wrong. So, what I'm about to share with
you is the single most important number
in your trading.
Your expectancy.
So, let me explain to you how this
works.
So, your expectancy can be defined using
this formula over here, right? Don't
don't be alarmed. I'll explain it to you
step by step so that, you know, even a
10-year-old can understand. So,
expectancy, the formula is defined by
your winning percentage multiplied by
your average gain minus your losing
percentage multiplied by your average
loss. So, your winning percentage
refers to, you know, how often you win.
So, if out of 10 trades you take, you
have six winners, four losers, it means
that you have a 60% winning rate, yeah?
And losing percentage is just how often
you lose, and in this case you have a
40% losing rate since you lost four
times out of 10.
Now, what about your average profit? How
do you define the average size of your
profit?
Again, let's say after 10 trades you
made $1,000 after 10 trades. So, this
means that your average profit per trade
is $1,000 divided by 10 because you took
10 trades. So, average profit is $100,
yeah? So, it is just the same for your
average loss. So, now let me walk you
through a couple of examples so you can
see this concept in action.
So, the first example, let's say you
have a trading system that has a 80%
winning rate.
Your average gain per trade is $10.
And your losing rate is 20%.
And your average loss is $100. So, what
is your expectancy?
So, if you plug in the formula, your
expectancy is
You can see your 80% over here is 0.8
multiplied by 10, which is your average
gain over here, minus 0.2, which is your
losing rate from this figure here, and
your average loss is $100, and then you
plug in over here. And what you realize
is that your expectancy is minus $12.
So,
what does this negative $12 mean?
This means that you can expect to lose
an average of $12 per trade.
And if you take 100 trades, you would be
roughly down about $1,200 after 100
trades. So, as you can see, even though
you win 80% of the time, the few losses
that you take, they're so devastating
that they actually wiped out all your
profits and more.
So, it's like being an amazing cook, an
amazing chef, you know, who
occasionally, you know, burns down the
entire house. Sure, you know, eight out
of 10 times you cook
amazing, good-tasting, delicious food.
But the other two times you need to call
on the fire department to put out the
fire in your house.
As you can tell, having a positive
expectancy, having an edge in the
markets is so, so, so important. So,
this is why I actually wrote this book
called Trading Systems That Work. You
can grab a copy for the link in the
description or go down to
tradingsystemsbook.com
and grab a copy. So, over here
you will learn not one, not two, but
three proven trading systems that work.
You will learn in this case a mean
reversion system here. You'll learn a
trend-following system and a breakout
trading system. I'll give you the exact
trading rules along with the back-tested
data so you can actually verify these
findings on your own and don't take my
word for it. And when you grab a copy of
this book today, you also get a number
of bonuses like the TradingView setup,
brokerage account setup, risk management
training, a community, private
community, and a trading systems cheat
sheet. So, all this comes along for free
when you grab a copy of this book called
Trading Systems That Work. So, if you're
interested, I'll put the link somewhere
below this video and you can grab a
copy. Now, you might be thinking, "Oh,
Rayner, if I just find a trading system
with the 80 90% winning rate and a
favorable risk to reward where I risk a
dollar and make back $3 or more, I'll be
rich."
Sorry to burst your bubble.
That's like wanting a six-pack abs while
eating anything you want.
It doesn't exist because there is always
a
trade-off.
Let me give you a real-world example,
okay? So, a mean reversion trading
system, they typically have a high
winning rate, you know, 60 plus percent,
sometimes even 70 percent, but a poor
risk to reward. That's because a mean
reversion trading system, it looks to
buy stocks when it's oversold.
And then sell when it makes
a bounce higher. And usually the bounces
are quite small. So, this type of
trading system typically have a high
winning rate, 60 plus 70% winning rate,
but the average profit is smaller than
the average loss. Why is that? That's
because you're taking quick profits on
the bounce.
But when a stock doesn't bounce, it can
keep falling
and falling
and falling. All right, just like my
hairline, right? Started receding at 30,
all right? 10 years later, it's still
going down lower. So, in other words,
you have a high winning rate, but a poor
risk to reward ratio. Let me give you an
example. For example, this is one of the
mean reversion trading system that I've
developed, and you can see that this
system has a positive expectancy in the
long run. You can see that.
From 2000, right? To now, right? The
equity curve is heading up in the right
direction over time. Although, of
course, you know, there's some bumps
along the way, right? Like pullbacks,
drawdowns along the way. And you can see
that for this particular system, the
winning rate is 66%. Can you see it?
In the long run, it's about 66%. And if
you look at the average profit
percentage, it's about 4.1%.
And the average loss percentage is 4.7,
close to 4.8%. So, in other words, all
right, your average loss is
slightly bigger than your average
profit. And again, as explained earlier,
because sometimes when you buy a stock,
it doesn't bounce, and it continue to,
you know, hit down lower and lower over
time.
On the other hand, you have trend
following, a type of trading system that
looks to ride trends in the market.
The winning rate for trend following is
usually low, between 35 to 45% and
you're wrong more often than you're
right. It can feel like, you know,
you're constantly getting punched by the
market. All right, on Monday you lose,
Tuesday you lose, Wednesday you lose,
Thursday you check your account and your
software ask you if you're okay. Even
the software feels sorry for you.
But when you do catch a trend, okay, the
payoff is massive. Right? Your average
profit will easily dwarf your average
loss. One good trend following trade can
pay off for multiple losses that you've
incurred earlier. So, kind of similar to
the fishing analogy that I shared with
you earlier.
So, in other words, a trend following
system has a low winning rate but a
favorable risk to reward ratio. Let me
give you an example.
So, this over here is a trend following
system that I've developed and you can
see again, this system has a positive
expectancy in the long run. The equity
curve is sloping up higher over time.
And what I want to bring your attention
to is over here.
Average winning rate is about 45%
in this case.
And you can see that the average profit
percentage for this is about 188%
and your average loss percentage is 99
percent, right? Don't don't don't get
freaked out by the numbers up because
with proper risk management and position
sizing, you're not going to lose 100% of
your account on each trade. But this is
just the way the
numbers are being reflected when we run
the back test for the system. So, you
can see over here, right? The message
is clear. For this system, you have a
45% winning rate but your gains are
almost twice the size of your losses.
So, this is why
as a trend follower, you may not win
often but when you win, you win big.
So, here's the deal. You can't have both
a high winning rate and a favorable risk
to reward. There's always a trade-off.
It's like marriage, you know, you can't
have someone who is always right or you
can have
peace. Ask me how I know about it.
You can't have both, right? Don't tell
my wife I said that.
This is why traders struggle, you know,
they expect to win 80 90% of the time
with an average of a 1:3, 1:4, 1:5 risk
to reward ratio. It It doesn't exist.
So, at this point, you've understood
what is expectancy and why it's so
important to have a profitable trading
system. But still, it is not enough if
you want to be a consistently profitable
trader because you also need
risk management, baby. So, risk
management protects your downside no
matter what happens, even if you have
10 20 losing trades in a row,
risk management is what helps you
survive so you can live to fight another
day because without it, even a
profitable trading system, even a
trading system that has a positive
expectancy,
will still fail. Let me give you an
example. So, imagine this. Imagine there
are two traders, John and Sally.
And let's say they both have a $10,000
trading account.
They have a trading system that has a
50% winning rate and an average of a 1:3
risk reward ratio. This means if they
risk uh
a $1,000 on a trade, a 1:3 risk reward
ratio means you'll get back $3,000 on
your winning trades. So, you can see
that clearly this trading system has an
edge, right? You have a positive
expectancy because your average gains is
bigger than your average loss.
And let's say John, you know, is the
type of trader that is aggressive, you
know, he he watches too many YouTube
videos of guys standing in front of
their rented Lamborghinis and telling
you that fortune favors the bold, yeah?
So, that's John. He risks $5,000 per
trade. And then you have Sally, who is
more conservative, risking $100 per
trade.
And then the next
10 trades are as follows, okay? This uh
is the outcome of the next 10 trades.
So, you can see over here you have, you
know, first few trades are lose, lose,
lose, lose, lose, followed by wins.
So, what is the outcome for both
traders? So, if you look at first, let's
look at John, shall we? Because
John
is the
aggressive one. You can see that. First
losing trade, he lose minus 5,000.
Second losing trade, lose again minus
another 5,000. And at this point, you
can see that John has pretty much
blown up, right? Because
minus five, minus five, negative
$10,000. And he start with $10,000,
nothing left after two trades.
On the other hand, let's say you have
Sally.
You can see that Sally risk $100 per
trade, and the first five trades are
losers, right? This five trades are
losing trades. So, total for Sally,
first five trades minus $500.
And because
she has proper risk management, she
managed to survive and see better days
ahead. And the next five trades are
winning trades. And as you know,
she gets an average of a one to three
risk reward ratio. This means on
average, her winning trades are three
times the size of her losses. So, in
total, she'll achieve about a positive
1,500 for
her five trades, right? Each trade is
about $300, 300, 300, 300, 300. So, net,
right? Sally, you can see she's actually
up $1,000
after
10 trades, whereas John has blown up
over here.
So, this is actually about a 10% gain
for Sally.
So,
can you see how important this is? You
can see that risk management is what
will protect your downside, right? So,
you can let the positive expectancy of
your trading play out over time.
So, how do you actually apply sound risk
management so that you don't blow up
your account like John? Well, this is
where you need to use a technique called
proper position sizing.
So, this refers to buying the right
number of shares according to your risk
management. So, let me teach you this
very useful technique.
Especially if you trade stocks, right?
So, the first step is this. Number one,
you must define the amount to risk,
usually 1 to 2% of your capital. So, let
me say for example, let's say you have a
$20,000 trading capital.
And if you want to risk 1% of your
account, this means 1% of $20,000 is
$200. This means you want to
buy the optimal number of shares such
that if the trade hits your stop loss,
you will lose not more than $200 per
trade. So, this is the first step first
step, right? To define the amount dollar
amount to risk, which is usually 1 to 2%
of your capital. So, another example,
let's say you have, you know, $100,000.
And if you're risking 2% of 100k, this
means you can
afford to lose up to $2,000 per trade.
Step two.
You then need to
You then need to take the dollar amount
that you want to risk divide by your
entry minus your stop loss. So,
So, let me give you a quick example. So,
entry refers to the entry price you're
entering the trade. Stop loss refers to
the level that you want to exit your
trade to cut your loss and move on.
And this dollar amount to risk is pretty
much defined over here in step one. So,
let me give you an example so you can
see how this works.
So, let's say for example, you have a
$100,000 trading account. You want to
risk 1% of your capital on each trade.
So, in other words, you want to risk
and lose not more than $1,000 on the
trade because 1% of $100,000 is $1,000.
Let's say your entry price, you know, to
place the trade is at $100. Maybe you
want to buy a breakout at $100. And your
stop loss is at $90. So, now the
question is, how many shares should you
buy? So, this is where again, step one,
define the dollar amount to risk. So,
just take 1%
of $100,000 and you get
$1,000. Step two,
position size the formula is equal to
the dollar amount that you want to risk,
which is a thousand dollars over here,
divided by your entry price minus your
stop loss. And in this case, you get 100
shares. Okay, so just plug in the
formula, 1,000
divided by 100 minus 90. 100 is from
your entry price, 90 is from your stop
loss, and you can
get 100 shares. So, this means you can
buy 100 shares of this stock
at the at the price of $100. And if you
were to hit your stop loss at $90, guess
what? You will lose, right? About $1,000
on this trade, which is the risk that
you have defined at the start.
Now, let me give you a another example
so I can explain a key concept.
Example two, right? Again, let's say you
have a hundred thousand dollars trading
account. You want to risk 1% of your
capital.
Entry price is 100 bucks, and this time
around your stop loss is wider. Your
stop loss now is at $80. How many shares
can you buy?
So, once again, plug in the formula,
define the dollar amount to risk, which
is a thousand dollars.
Step two, your position size is defined
by the amount to risk divided by your
entry minus stop loss. And in this case,
you realize that you can buy a total of
50 shares.
Okay, so do you see how how this works?
If you recall earlier, you can buy 100
shares because
your stop loss level was at $90.
See the difference?
$90 stop loss, entry price is the same,
and you can buy 100 shares.
And in the second example, you can buy
50 shares because this time around your
stop loss got wider. Instead of 90
bucks, now it's at $80. So, the message
that I'm trying to bring across here is
this, is that your position size depends
on the size of your stop loss, whether
how tight or how wide it is.
A tighter stop loss means you can buy
more shares, and a wider stops means you
can buy fewer shares. And either way,
the dollar amount you risk stays the
same.
Now, a mistake that many traders make is
they have a habit of buying the same
number of shares regardless of
the stocks that they are trading. So,
what I mean by this is that, you know,
let's say they have a habit of always
buying, you know, 100 shares. But, as
you know, if you buy 100 shares for a
stock like McDonald's versus 100 shares
for a stock like Nvidia, you can see
that your
risk
is not going to be constant because for
Nvidia, buying 100 shares, the stock is
more volatile. Usually, you would have a
wider stop loss to take into account
that volatility. And by using a wider
stop loss and still buying that same 100
shares, you could potentially lose more
money compared to a more
lower volatility stock like McDonald's,
where you won't have such a huge stop
loss. So, by using that fixed 100 shares
across all the different stocks that
you're trading, regardless of time frame
and stuff like that, what's going to
happen is that you realize that
sometimes when you are wrong, your
losses can far exceed your
winners. Yeah? And there will also be
times where sometimes when you are
right, then you realize, "Why is my
profit so so small?" Yeah? Because,
again, position sizing. You need to
adjust it according to the size of your
stop loss, and your size of your stop
loss is, you know, influenced by the
volatility of the stock that you're
trading.
So, now, at this point, you've learned
what is expectancy,
risk management, and proper position
sizing.
So, however, I can tell you that, you
know, after a few losses, many traders,
they will start to doubt the trading
system. They will second-guess their
trades, and, you know, eventually
abandon the trading system, right? I've
been there myself. And why is that?
That's because
in the short run, your trading results
is actually random. Let me explain. Now,
imagine you toss a coin, right? A normal
legit coin, right? Whether it's a dollar
or 50 cents, doesn't matter. I'm sure
you can agree that there is a 50% chance
that coin will either come up head
or tail, right? Duh.
Now, let me ask you. If you toss the
coin 10 times, okay? Just, you know, do
it 10 times.
Are you guaranteed to get five heads and
five tails?
Think about this. Think about this. I'll
give you 5 seconds.
1 2 3 4 5, okay?
And the answer is no. Of course not. You
could get, you know, four head, six
tails. You could could get three heads,
seven tails,
you know, and whatnot.
So, you won't definitely get five heads
and five tails. And
why? Why is that so?
And the reason is simple.
It's because
you didn't toss the coin
enough.
The frequency of your coin toss isn't
So, let me give you an example so you
know what I mean.
So, after tossing a coin 10 times, you
could get, you know, four heads and six
tails. We call this a 40% hit rate, not
a winning rate because, you know, it's
not it's not trading or investing. So,
we call this a 40% hit rate.
And now, what happens if you now toss
the coin 100 times? How would your hit
rate change? Well, after 100 times, you
probably will get something like
45 heads and 55 tails, and that's about
a 45%
hit rate, right? With reference to the
the number of times you get hit, right?
So, just you take 45
divide by the number of times you toss
the coin, you get 45%.
And what if you now toss the coin 1,000
times? How will your hit rate change?
Well, in this case, you get something
like, you know, possibly 480 heads and
520 tails, a 48% hit rate.
And do you do you do you see the
pattern?
Right? Do you see the pattern? You can
see that the more time you flip the
coin, the closer you get to that 50%
probability. And this is a very
important
concept. This is a concept that we call
the law of large number.
Now, the law of large number applies to
anything that deals with probabilities,
whether you're tossing a coin, whether
you're investing, whether you're
trading.
And this is a concept where
in the short run, your results, your
trading results is actually random.
And it's only in the long run, it'll
align towards your trading system's
expectancy.
So, the message that I want to bring
over here is that don't abandon your
trading system system, especially if you
know that it's a proven trading system
backed by data. Don't abandon it after a
few losses. Because the outcome is is
random. You can have a trading system
with a 70% winning rate, but maybe you
take 10 trades, you could have
experienced
six losses and four winners, and you
think it's only a 40% winning rate. But
no, it's because you didn't execute
enough trades for your trading system
expectancy to play out. So, don't
abandon the the system after a few
losses. You need time. You need to give
your trading system time
for its edge to play out. You with me?
Do you agree? Right?
Smash the thumbs up button and hit
subscribe, right, if you do.
At this point, you have learned quite a
few mathematical concepts and
techniques. So, let me share with you a
recap Give you a quick recap of what
we've covered today.
First, we talked about the expectancy.
What is expectancy and the formula
behind it? So, as you've learned, right,
your winning rate, your risk-to-reward
ratio on its own, these metrics are, you
know, they are
useless. It doesn't give you the full
picture. What you need to know is the
expectancy, whether your system has a
positive expectancy or not. And that
formula is defined by this: your winning
percentage multiplied by your average
gain minus your losing percentage
multiplied by your average loss. And if
you have a positive expectancy, it means
that you have an edge in the markets and
you're going to make money in the long
run when you have a trading system that
gives you a positive expectancy.
Then you've learned that having
expectancy is one thing, but it's not
enough because you also need sound risk
management to protect your downside so
you can leave to fight another day, so
you can survive the drawdown. Yeah? And
the way we manage our risk is through
proper position sizing and I explained
to you the formula, the math behind it.
Step one is to define the dollar amount
to risk, usually about 1 to 2% of your
trading capital. Once you've done that,
then you need to calculate your position
size using this formula over here, which
is the dollar amount that you want to
risk divided by your entry minus your
stop loss. And you've learned that
usually when you have a wider stop loss,
you would
have a smaller position size. And if
your stop loss is tighter,
you would have a larger position size.
And finally, we've also talked about the
law of large numbers. Right? This is
important because in the short run your
trading results
is random, right? And in the in the long
run you're aligned towards your trading
system expectancy. So don't abandon your
system, you know, just because of a few
losing trades because you are then, you
know, kind of like giving up too early.
Yeah? So
this is a quick recap. And for those of
you who are wondering, "Noraina, you
know, how do I then, you know, get, you
know, trading systems that work? How do
I know that my trading system actually
has an edge in the market?" Well, if you
feel that way, then I've written a book
over here called Trading Systems That
Work. I'll put the link somewhere below
this video so you can grab a copy or
just go down to Trading Systems
Book.com. And this book, you'll learn
not one, not two, but three proven
trading systems that work. They're all
backed by data so you can actually
verify it on your own. And
here's the deal, right? You know,
I'm going to, you know, make this
risk-free for you. You can, you know,
grab a copy of this book and read it and
if you don't get value out of it, right?
You know, just feel free to drop us an
email, right?
Within the first 180 days and we'll
happily refund you in full and you can
still, you know, keep the book, right?
Just as our way of, you know, saying
thank you, right? For being supportive
of our work over the years. So, I'll put
the link somewhere somewhere below this
video so you can grab a copy and with
that said, I wish you good luck, good
trading. I'll be talking to you soon.